"Fat-Blocking Benefits of Hibiscus Tea"
Hibiscus tea, also known as roselle or
Jamaica, is enjoyed around the world
hot or cold for its bright red color
and tart cranberry-like flavor.
It's the "zing" in Red Zinger tea.
I talk about its benefits
in the chapter
on high blood pressure
in How Not to Die,
working as well as some leading
antihypertensive medications
in head-to-head tests, or
even beating the drugs out.
Within three hours
of drinking hibiscus tea,
changes in hundreds
of metabolites can be detected
in the human bloodstream
with creative names
like hibiscic acid, or
hibiscin, or hibiscitrin.
Alterations in human gene
expression at the 3-hour mark
after drinking it suggest
a downregulation
of cholesterol synthesis and
an improvement in metabolism.
But randomized controlled trials
failed to consistently find
cholesterol-lowering benefits.
An interesting side-effect
popped up, though: weight loss.
In Mexico, hibiscus tea
has been traditionally used
as a treatment for obesity,
sparking lots of research interest.
Computer modeling studies
have suggested that
certain hibiscus compounds
might bind
to the fat-digesting enzyme
lipase like a lock-and-key.
Test tube studies screening
a variety of medicinal plants
did indeed find hibiscus
inhibited lipase
more than most of the others,
and hibiscus has been found
to reduce body fat in hamsters,
mice, and rats,
increasing fecal fat excretion.
But it wasn't tested in people
until this study published in 2014.
The title gives the findings away.
Spoiler alert: Hibiscus can inhibit
obesity and fat accumulation --
in humans -- and improve fatty liver.
To create a randomized
double-blind trial,
instead of trying to create
some artificially colored
and flavored placebo tea,
they just dried the hibiscus tea
into powder and put it into capsules.
After 12 weeks, there was
a greater reduction in waistlines
and percent body fat
in the hibiscus group,
compared to those who
got placebo capsules.
But the dose they ended up using
was equivalent
of like nine cups
of hibiscus tea a day.
I recommend people stick
to no more than a quart a day
on a regular basis due to
the high manganese content.
Manganese is an
essential trace mineral,
but nine cups a day might result
in too much of a good thing.
Finally, in 2018, this study was
published using a reasonable dose --
the equivalent of about a single
12-ounce glass of hibiscus tea a day.
The complicating factor is that they
also added lemon verbena to the mix.
That's another herbal tea, better
known for improving recovery
after intense bouts
of strength training,
but there was some promising
in vitro data on effects
of lemon verbena
on fat cells in a petri dish,
so they tried a combination.
It comes out to be about
a cup and a half of hibiscus tea
and a quarter cup of lemon verbena
tea once a day for two months.
Both the tea and placebo
groups were fed diets
containing the same amount
of calories, yet those randomized
to the tea group lost
significantly more weight --
five pounds compared
to three pounds.
That's only an extra
pound or two a month,
but an extra pound a month
eating the same number of calories.
That's the advantage of
fat-blocking interventions
that actually cause you
to lose more calories
beyond just reducing hunger
and making you feel fuller longer
in hopes you'll eat fewer
calories in the first place.
Why not just pop pills
instead of brewing tea?
There's all sorts of herbal extract
supplements on the market,
but that presumes we know
enough to extract out
the right active ingredients.
For example, it does not appear
to be the red anthocyanin pigments
in hibiscus, since white varieties
seem to have similar effects.
When the various compounds
in hibiscus tea are isolated out
and tested in various combinations,
synergistic effects are found,
meaning the whole may be
greater than the sum of its parts.
As with any sour food or beverage,
though (like after eating citrus),
it's important to wash the
natural acids off your teeth
by rinsing your mouth out with
water to protect your tooth enamel.
You also want to wait
at least an hour before brushing,
so as not to erode your enamel
when it's in a softened state.